A Finding Aid to the Ilse Martha Bischoff Papers, 1893-1981, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ilse Martha Bischoff papers
1893-1981
Archives of American Art
Bischoff, Ilse, 1901-1990
AAA.biscilse
Archival Resource Key
1.2 Linear feet
The papers of illustrator, writer and collector Ilse Martha Bischoff measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1893-1981. Found are scattered personal and business records, correspondence, pencil and watercolor sketches, notes and writings, printed material and photographs. Correspondence is primarily with family members and colleagues including Paul Cadmus and Jared French. Photographs are of Bischoff, her family, and colleagues including Paul Cadmus and Jared French.
Biographical Note
Ilse Martha Bischoff was born on November 21, 1901 in New York City, to Adele Maria Timme Bischoff and Ernst Bischoff, founder of the Ernst Bischoff (pharmaceuticals) Company of Ivoryton, Connecticut.
Bischoff began her education at the Horace Mann School, later studying costume design at the Parson's School of Design. At the Art Students League, she studied painting under Frank Du Mond and etching with Joseph Pennell. While at the Art Students League, Bischoff befriended painters Paul Cadmus and Jared French. She also studied art in Paris, France, and Munich, Germany.
From 1928 to 1946, Bischoff illustrated 12 books and wrote two novels about George Washington's Portraitist, Gilbert Stuart: Painter's Coach in 1943, and Proud Heritage in 1949. Her autobiography, Drive Slowly: Six Dogs, was published in 1953. She was also an avid collector of Meissen porcelain.
Bishoff's artwork is represented in the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the New York Public Library, the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston and the Hood Museum at Dartmouth.
Ilse Martha Bischoff died December 5, 1990, in Hartland, Vermont.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of illustrator, writer and collector Ilse Martha Bischoff measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1893-1981. Found are scattered personal and business records, correspondence, pencil and watercolor sketches, notes and writings, printed material and photographs.
Correspondence is primarily with family members and colleagues including Paul Cadmus and Jared French. Artwork includes pencil and watercolor sketches, and notes and writings consist primarily of typescripts of Bischoff's short stories. Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material relating to Bischoff's European travel. Of special interest are photographs of Bischoff, her family, and colleagues including Paul Cadmus and Jared French.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Personal Records, 1934-1938, 1955-1968 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1922-1981 (Box 1; 47 folders)
Series 3: Artwork, circa 1920-circa 1959 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1929-1975 (Box 1; 33 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1929-1976 (Box 1; 15 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, 1893-1971 (Box 2; 20 folders)
Provenance
The Ilse Martha Bischoff papers were donated in 1980-1981 by the artist.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Collectors -- New York (State) -- New York; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Women artists; Women painters; Women authors; Sketches; Writings; Photographs; French, Jared, 1905-1988; Cadmus, Paul, 1904-1999
- Personal Records, 1934-1938, 1955-1968; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a description and blueprint of Bishchoff's property in Hartland, Vermont, a kennel name certificate, and miscellaneous receipts, as well as Bischoff's passport documenting trips to Germany, France and Great Britain.
  - Blueprint and Description of Bishchoff's Property and a Kennel Name Certificate, 1955-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passport, 1934-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1922-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 47 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence consists primarily of an exchange of letters between Bischoff and her sister Carola Bischoff and her husband, Harold Graves Terwilliger, whose nicknames were "Ollie" and "Twig." There are also letters exchanged with colleagues including artists Paul Cadmus, Jared French, Felix Kelly, and Ivan Albright, writers Mabel Louise Robinson, and Glenway Wescott, and design consultant John Wisner. One letter from Cadmus is illustrated with cartoons of road signs and gives directions to his house. There are several letters from collector of porcelain Ralph H. Wark. There is also a postcard from Prince Karlos Biorn von Kurland displaying a photograph of the Prince and his wife.
  Arrangement note
  Undated correspondence is followed by chronological correspondence.
  - Letters from Gerald, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose First Initials Begin "H-V,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose Surnames Begin "A,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Ilse Bischoff to Carola Terwilliger, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Ilse Bischoff to Miscellaneous Recipients, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose Surnames Begin "C-M,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose Surnames Begin "N-Q,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose Surnames Begin "R-S,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Members of the Terwilliger Family, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Correspondents Whose Surnames Begin "T-Z,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-50)
- Artwork, circa 1920-circa 1959; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Artwork consists of pencil and watercolor sketches of human figures and poodles, primarily for use as book illustrations.
  - Pencil and Watercolor Sketches, circa 1920-circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Notes and Writings, 1929-1975; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 33 Folders Box 1
  This series includes research notes for Bischoff's writing, notes about daily activities written in text form, an inventory list of her porcelain collection, and manuscripts and typescripts of miscellaneous writings. There is also a carbon copy of a manuscript about Bischoff written by Paul Cadmus.
  - Notes for a Biography of Madame Vigée-Le Brun, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
  - Notes on Daily Activities, 1950-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Inventory of Bischoff's Porcelain Collection, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Notes on Joseph II, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1929, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous Untitled Manuscripts, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Manuscript "Richie,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous Untitled Typescripts, 1955-1963, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62-67)
  - Typescript "Catherine the Great and Frederick Melchior Grimm as Revealed Through Their Correspondence,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Typescript "The Dog with the Three-Way Tail,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Typescript "Fluke,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Typescript "The Humperdinck's Christmas Eve,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Typescript "Jeppy,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72-73)
  - Typescript "No One Need Know,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Typescript "My Onkel Karl,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Typescript "Poodle in Paris,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76-78)
  - Typescript "Single Accommodations,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Typescript "Treasures of a Woodland Floor,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Typescript "A Warm Place,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Typescript "Pumpernickle the Lonely Dachshund,", 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Typescript "Old Holden: A Portrait,", 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Manuscript about Bischoff by Paul Cadmus, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Printed Material, 1929-1976; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 15 Folders Box 1
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, a press release, programs for Italian and German opera performances, German tour booklets, brochures for children's books and a festival in Salzburg, Austria, picture postcards of artwork and scenic European views, and a calling card for Ernst Bischoff.
  - Clippings, 1934-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 86-88)
  - Press Release, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Programs, 1960-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 90-93)
  - German Tour Booklets, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1949-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Picture Postcards of Miscellaneous Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Picture Postcards of Germany, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Picture Postcards of Italy and France, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1929, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 99)
- Photographs, 1893-1971; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 20 Folders Box 2
  Photographs are of Bischoff, her family, and her colleagues including painters Paul Cadmus and Jared French, and design consultant John Wisner. There are also photographs of artwork executed between 1935-1965 and of figurines and dishes from Bischoff's porcelain collection.
  - Photographs of Ilse Bischoff, 1926-1938, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Bishcoff Family Members, 1893-1934, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
  - Photographs of Ilse Bischoff and Friends, 1924-1958, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs of a Costume Party, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Bischoff's Home "High Meadows,", 1961-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of the Home of Bischoff's Grandparents, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Uncle Karl's Castello on Lake Lugano, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Drawings, 1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs of Paintings, 1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Photographs of Porcelain Figurines, 1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Porcelain Dishes, 1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Reference Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)